All right, we'll start.
Does anybody not hear?
You're all here?
Okay, let's do drug toxicities on page 26.
Bad news, you got to know your drug toxicities.
Good news, you don't have to know them all.
You just need to know what everybody else knows.
And if anybody knows drug toxicities, they know these five.
Anything beyond these five is really nuts to know.
It's not really need to know territory.
You do need to know these five though.
I would really suggest that this is a little bit of memory work, but it's a good payoff
for it.
Because you understand this is a test for nurse safety.
And one of the biggest ways you can be unsafe is to not know drug toxic effects.
You see how that could result in real patient harm.
So that's an area they like to test is toxic reactions to drugs, drug toxicities.
So let's talk about these five.
Lithium.
Lithium of course is the famous anti-mania drug.
It's used for bipolar, but it's not used for the depression.
It's used for the mania.
It's therapeutic level in the middle column there.
You should write 0.6 to 1.2.
Now the toxic level is greater than or equal to 2.
Now immediately you should see that there is a gray area there where you're higher than
1.2, but under 2.0.
You see that gray area?
That is a gray area where no books agree on exactly what's going on with lithium at those
levels.
From 0.6 to 1.2 everyone agrees that it is therapeutic.
Everyone agrees that two and over is toxic.
Now in between you just pick your book and they're going to say different things.
One of the things that you guys don't know about me, well maybe you do know about me
that probably is good for you to know about me and help you understand why I say what
I do and how I say what I do is that for years I was an NCLEX RN item test writer.
I wrote questions on the NCLEX.
So the questions that were on there I've written some of those questions.
So I've been through the whole training protocol on how they want you to write questions for
them.
So when I tell you that questions are written this way that's because I've been through
the in-service education on it and I've been trained as their item writer.
In 2003 I think it was, maybe it was 2002, somewhere right around in there the NCSBN
made a rule that you cannot be an item writer and be a NCLEX reviewer at the same time.
Which makes sense.
You can't write the questions and then go teach people how to pass the test.
It's not ethically correct.
So at that time I had to pick between writing questions and reviewing and I picked reviewing
and so I stopped writing questions and so I haven't written a question since 2003 roughly.
But if they only change 5% every year there's still loads of questions on there that I've
written.
Now I say that to tell you that when I give you ranges, the ranges I give you may not
be the ones you learned but they are the ones that you use when you write questions.
Did you see what I'm saying?
And most of the time my ranges are wider than what you, most of the times than what you
learned because the instructions are to every item writer on the boards is when you write
a test question where you use a lab value or a range, a value in a range, a number,
go to at least five different books published by five different publishers and see what
they say.
The ranges then make your range wide enough to fit all of those.
Did you see what I'm saying?
So the books one says one to two, book two says one to 2.3, book three says 0.8 to 1.8
to 1.9.
Well you've got to go from 0.8 to 2.3 as your range.
That way it's a fair question no matter what book the student's used.
So you're going to see my ranges are different but my ranges are made to fit the NCLEX.
Do you understand that?
And not necessarily a particular book.
So you may use my ranges and my numbers and you may go take the, like the Saunders review
book with questions or the exam cram with questions or the NCLEX gold with questions
and using my ranges you may miss the question.
Why?
Because they went by their ranges.
What ranges?
The ranges in the MedSearch book that that company publishes.
Only one book, not five.
Now Kaplan does what I do.
Anybody that's a national reviewer does what I do which is a wider range than normal.
So here's the deal.
Boards would never give you a lithium of 1.3, 1.4, 1.5, 1.6, 1.7, 1.8, 1.9.
Why?
It's in that gray area where books don't agree and item writers have to get it to where all
the books agree.
So I teach you two and greater because every book agrees that that is toxic.
Alrighty?
So don't worry about that when you see these ranges.
Okay, lanoxone.
Lanoxone, what's the other name for it?
I told you yesterday you have to know this.
DIG.
This is used to treat basically two things.
DIG is used to treat afib and congestive heart fib.
Atrial fib and congestive heart failure.
How should you have already known that it treats atrial fib?
DIG.
In what context did we talk about DIG yesterday?
Adena, beta, calcium, DIG.
So DIG is the D of the ABCDs of atrial treatment.
So atrial fib, yes.
And then congestive heart failure is the other big one that it treats.
Well, what is the therapeutic level of DIG?
One to two.
And you notice I'm not giving you units, correct?
Because what did I tell you about units?
Don't worry about it.
They're not going to ask you.
They're going to say, how many milligrams per deciliter of?
And you just say the number.
This toxic level is greater than or equal to two.
So what do you notice about two?
It could be therapeutic and it could be toxic.
So what do you call it when they give you a value of two?
Toxic why?
It's safer to call something toxic when it may not be than to say it's therapeutic when
it might not be.
So always err on that safe side.
What do you notice about lithium and linoxins toxicities?
They're the same at two and greater.
Aminophilin.
Aminophilin is a airway anti-spasmodic.
It relieves spasms in your airway.
It is technically not a bronchodilator.
What do I mean by that?
It's technically not a bronchodilator.
What does it not do?
It doesn't stimulate your beta-2 agonist cell.
It's just bronchodilate.
It just relaxes a spasm.
Now when you're in a spasm, your airway is what?
Narrow or wide?
And when I relax a spasm, what happens is the airway gets what?
Wider.
It actually looks like it's a bronchodilator, but it's not really a bronchodilator.
Epinephrine is a bronchodilator.
Hypotroprin is a bronchodilator.
Alupent, albuterol is it?
Arbongodilator.
Turbutylin is a bronchodilator.
This is a muscle spasm relaxer.
Has anybody ever, and I'm sort of just going off the side here on these things just to
see if you can apply some stuff.
Have you ever seen anybody come in or heard of anyone coming in in an acute asthmatic
attack and the bronchodilators aren't working?
That happens on occasion.
Probably what's happening.
Why are the bronchodilators working?
What's that?
I really can't hear you, Mr. Trump.
Okay, the inflammation, but there's a bigger reason.
They're in a spasm.
They're in acute, locked down spasm.
And the bronchodilator isn't going to work because the spasm is in the way.
So what do you have to give them first?
Some aminophilin to do what to the spasm?
Relieve the spasm.
Then you can come in with a bronchodilator and it will work.
So just remember when a bronchodilator doesn't work in an acute airway problem, give them
a theophilin, give them an aminophilin, and that will melt the spasm and then the bronchodilator
will work.
Yes?
A lot of times when little kids come in with acute, reactive airway disease, they'll slap
them on an aminophilin drip and then start giving them breathing treatments with betas.
And they may have 20 of them.
And the first 19 may not work until that aminophilin kicks in and then the 19th one works.
You see?
So I've seen little kids.
What's the most breathing treatments you've seen in airway?
Have you ever in work ER in children's stuff ever?
What's the most?
Nobody's...
Okay.
Well then it's a no question.
But I have seen up to 20 breathing treatments being given in a row for these little kids.
It's really just phenomenal.
Okay.
That's not typical.
That's the extreme.
All right.
What's the therapeutic level?
10 to 20.
There again, don't worry about units.
Any aminophilin under 10 is what?
If you get an aminophilin level of 8, what's that mean?
So they need to take more.
Or are they taking it?
Okay.
If it's 21, what's it mean?
It's toxic.
But anything in between 10 and 20 is therapeutic.
What if it's 20?
Because 20 toxicity is greater than or equal to 20 on this one.
So 20 could be either way, so you call it toxic if you have to.
So aminophilin toxic is greater than or equal to 20.
Dilanthin, what is this used for?
Does anybody know what dilanthin or phenytoin?
Seizure.
Seizure, yeah.
Its therapeutic level is 10 to 20.
And its toxicity is greater than or equal to 20.
So what do you call 20?
Not faster.
Although it may be therapeutic.
Billie Rubin.
Billie Rubin is not a drug.
It's a waste product from the breakdown of red blood cells.
When boards test Billie Rubin, they will only test it in newborns.
They will never test it in adults.
Does anybody know what the normal adult Billie Rubin is?
It's like 1 to 2.
You know, 1.4 to 2.3, something like that.
It's really low.
But in newborns, newborns have high Billie Rubens all the time.
Why?
What are they doing?
Breaking down.
Which red blood cells?
The moths.
So babies will run Billie Rubens at 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
And that's fine.
Now, if I had an 8 Billie Rubin right now, they'd have my rear end in a bed over there
finding out what's wrong with me.
But a newborn with an 8 is no big deal.
So what I want you to do with this Billie Rubin is you see where it says therapeutic
level, the middle column.
In the box for Billie Rubin, I want you to write the word elevated level.
So what is the elevated range for Billie Rubin in a newborn?
10 to 20.
So what does it mean when a Billie Rubin in a newborn is 9.9 and less?
It's normal, but it's high for an adult, but it's normal.
So we don't even get concerned about newborn Billie Rubens until it hits what number?
10.
Which is 10 times 5 to 10 times more than what an adult should have.
So what is the Billie Rubin toxicity?
Greater than or equal to 20.
So when do you suppose a child, a child with what Billie Rubin and above do you think needs
to come into the hospital?
Certainly before, what about before 10?
No.
And even at 10, 11 and 12, what are they?
Is it elevated?
But you can manage it at home with sunlight, drinking a lot, flushing that Billie Rubin out.
It's usually right about 14 to 15 that docs start thinking about hospitalizing these kids.
About 14 or 15.
Because once you hit 15, where are you in the scheme of things overall?
You're halfway to what?
You're halfway to toxic.
And once you hit toxic, they can die.
So you don't want it to be 18 or 17 or 19.
That's way too close.
You just don't like that.
So but most docs will not bring in a 12 or a 13.
They'll usually wait till 14.
Some docs wait till 15.
I don't see any docs that wait till 16.
I just typically not.
Okay, so halfway through the elevated range, they start to hospitalize.
Now, what do you notice about those toxic levels?
What pattern do you see?
Two's and 20's.
Which ones are the two's?
lithium and Linux.
And we start with what letter?
So you pick the lower number with the ones with L.
So lithium, Linux and go low.
Two.
Billy Rubin, Ammon, Offlin, Delanten, go high, go 20.
So you're usually picking between 2 and 20.
And those are the major ones that they talk about.
All right, what about current interest and epistatons?
Do you see those words right there?
You need to know these words, these vocabulary words.
What does current interest mean?
Does anyone know what current interest means?
Billy Rubin in the brain.
When your Billy Rubin crosses your blood-brain barrier
and it's in your cerebral spinal fluid, it's in your brain, it's in your meninges,
you have current interest.
So current interest, okay, what's jaundice?
It's a yellow color due to...
Billy Rubin in the skin.
What's current interest?
Billy Rubin in the brain.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So jaundice is Billy Rubin in the skin, current interest is Billy Rubin in the brain.
Both are due to Billy Rubin, it's just where is it?
Current interest usually occurs when you get up around 20.
When your Billy Rubin gets around 20, you start going current interest.
Do you see why it's so dangerous?
Because Billy Rubin, when it gets into your brain, it causes what we call aseptic.
What does that mean? Aseptic.
A means what?
Without sepsis means infection.
So aseptic means no germs.
It causes aseptic meningitis, aseptic encephalitis,
which means a sterile encephalitis due to the irritation of the Billy Rubin.
You don't have to know all that.
Just know that when your Billy Rubin gets to be 20,
you go kernectic and you could die.
The baby could.
Now, opisthetonus, does anybody know what that is?
I told you we learned a lot of vocabulary this week.
What's opisthetonus?
Okay, it's a position the baby assumes when they have Billy Rubin on the brain.
It's a position.
Kernectorus is a condition.
Opisthetonus is a position.
And what they do is they hyperextend.
These babies hyperextend due to the irritation of the meninges with the Billy Rubin.
So these babies hyperextend.
Now, what do you know about the flexibility of a newborn?
No flexibility or unbelievable flexibility.
Unbelievable.
So when they extend, literally their heels will come up and touch their ears.
They will be like in a back walkover.
You know, they'll be completely, and they'll be very rigid in that.
They'll hyperextend.
They almost look like they're dis-cerebrating, if you've ever heard of dis-cere-bration.
They look, they're hyper-extending.
When you see that, when you see a little kid whose Billy Rubin is 15, okay,
he came in, Billy Rubin 15, and he starts extending his neck, what do you think?
Is that something that needs to follow up right away immediately, medical emergency?
Yes, because he could be going into opisthetonus because he's kernicturing.
And you want to catch it right away.
Now, the question that often is asked on boards and other standardized tests is,
in what position do you place an opisthetonic child?
Now, think about it.
If they're hyperextending like this, what's a good position to put them in?
On their side.
You can't put them on their back.
You can't put them on their abdomen.
You have to put them on their side.
Okay, that's it on drug toxicities.
Just remember your 2s and your 20s.
Yes?
The only thing that they don't test is on the hour, on the day, on the boards.
The only thing that boards will do there is they'll talk about pathologic jaundice versus
physiologic jaundice.
And physiologic jaundice, the bilirubin is high and the kid is yellow at birth.
With pathologic jaundice, no, reverse that.
Pathologic is high at birth and the kid's yellow at birth.
Physiologic jaundice, the kid's bilirubin is low at birth, not well, normal at birth.
And over the next 2 to 3 days goes high on bilirubin.
So here's the deal.
If they come out yellow, something's wrong.
It's pathologic.
If they come out yellow.
If they turn yellow over the next few days, that's typical expected.
But they're not going to, they're just going to ask about whether it's present at birth or develops on day 2, day 3, and which one's pathologic, which one's physiologic.
And they won't get any more specific than that.
Which is in the blue book, you know, so you've got to remember that blue book too.
Hey, dumping syndrome versus hyaluronia.
These are very commonly tested things on boards, particularly dumping syndrome.
They really like to talk about dumping syndrome.
It shows up a lot.
Definitions.
What is hyaluronia?
Well, I like to talk about these two together because they're both gastric, emptying problems.
And they're kind of opposites.
And I like to remember opposites together.
Why?
Memorize one and you got the other.
That's why diabetes, and syphilis, and SIADH, I'm only going with one, figuring the other one out.
Well, let's talk about what hyaluronia is.
Hyaluronia is regurgitation of acid, meaning acid comes back up into your esophagus, where it's not supposed to be,
because the upper part of your stomach permeates upward through the diaphragm.
You're not supposed to have, where's all, your stomach is supposed to be 100% in your abdominal cavity, right?
With hyaluronia, you have a two-chambered stomach.
You got two, you're like a cow. You got two stomachs.
Typically, this is your thorax here.
Okay, and here's your diaphragm separating your abdominal cavity below from your thoracic cavity above.
The esophagus comes down like this, and then the stomach is there.
It's supposed to be all below this diaphragm.
In hyaluronia, what happens is part of it goes up like this,
and you've got a two-chambered stomach with a band around the middle.
And what happens when you eat, it sort of sits right here, and then comes right back up.
That's the problem with hyaluronia.
Now, below the line there, do you see where it says gastric contents move?
Gastric contents move in the right or wrong direction?
Wrong direction at the correct rate.
In other words, does the stomach empty faster or slower or at a normal rate?
Well, it empties at a normal rate. The rate's not the problem.
With hyaluronia, the rate is not the problem. It is the direction that is the problem.
It's moving in the wrong direction at the correct rate.
Now, let's compare that with something called dumping syndrome.
Dumping syndrome, again, is a gastric problem.
It usually follows gastric surgery in which the gastric contents dump too quickly into the duodenum.
Now, are your gastric contents supposed to go into your duodenum? Yes.
So what's the problem? It's too fast.
So in this case, the gastric contents move in the right direction at the wrong rate.
So you see where they're opposites?
One is correct rate, wrong direction. The other is wrong rate, correct direction.
They flip-flop.
So if these were speeding tickets that you...if not speeding, if these were traffic violations you got,
if these were traffic violations, what would you be cited for in hyaluronia?
Going the wrong way on a one-way street, correct?
What would you be cited for with dumping syndrome? Speeding.
So one's a speed issue, one's a direction issue.
All right, what are the signs and symptoms?
Well, hyaluronia is real easy.
The signs and symptoms of hyaluronia are just plain GERD.
G-E-R-D.
Gastroesophageal reflux disease.
In other words, heartburn and indigestion to state it simply.
So when you see GERD, don't freak out. It's just heartburn and indigestion, no baby.
But let me tell you something.
Hyaluronia is a specific case here.
You can have GERD for a hundred different reasons, one of which is hyaluronia.
What makes GERD hyaluronia is this.
Hyaluronia is GERD if you lie down after you eat.
If you have indigestion and heartburn, it doesn't mean you have hyaluronia.
You could have it, but it doesn't mean you do have it.
I'm going to give you two examples, and you tell me which one has GERD and which one has hyaluronia.
A nurse gets up in the morning, skips breakfast, goes to work, passes a whole floor of meds, does a bunch of treatments,
and at 11 o'clock gets epigastric burning pain, burping, indigestion, and it really hurts,
and they've got to drink some milk or something.
It hurts. Do they have GERD? Yes. Do they have hyaluronia? Why not?
You aren't lying down and you didn't eat.
Okay, but what about this patient?
A nurse gets off at 7 p.m., goes home, eats dinner at 8 o'clock, sits down and watches TV,
half hour later eats a bowl of cereal, 20 minutes later eats a bag of chips,
20 minutes later eats ice cream and chocolate syrup.
Then they get tired, and 10 minutes later they go to bed.
Half hour later they wake up with burning, epigastric pain, indigestion, and they go, oh, it hurts.
Same set of symptoms that the other nurse had. Could this person have hyaluronia? Why?
They lay down right after they ate.
You cannot have hyaluronia unless your symptoms occur when you're lying down after you eat.
If you have GERD at a random time, so you don't have hyaluronia.
Hyaluronia is dependent upon position and meal time.
That's hyaluronia. It's just indigestion and heartburn when you lie down after you eat.
Okay, dumping syndrome, and they like to test dumping syndrome, and it's a huge list of signs.
The easiest way I know to remember all the things that happen in dumping syndrome is to take what I already know
and combine it to equal dumping syndrome. So what do I want you to take?
Well, first off, if you want to know what a person looks like with dumping syndrome, the first thing is talk about drunk.
Okay, what's a drunk person look like?
Saguar and gait, slurred speech, impaired, judgment delayed, reaction time, emotional.
What's the fancy word? Lay vile emotions.
Well, all that can be dumping syndrome because with dumping syndrome you do have cerebral impairment
because of decreased blood flow to the brain because all the blood's going to the gut because it dumped into the duod.
Then you also get shock. Signs of shock, which are what?
Hypotension, tachycardia, tachypnea, what's the skin?
Pale, cold, clammy. Cold because you don't have any blood there?
S
The drunk plus shock equals hypoglycemia.
Well, to get dumping syndrome, you add to that acute abdominal distress.
And what belongs on the list of acute abdominal distress signs and symptoms?
When someone has acute abdominal distress, describe them for me.
Cramping, pain, doubling over, guarding, protecting, what else?
What would you hear with the stethoscope?
Hyperactive. Boreboregmy, thank you.
Yes, hyperactive vessels, but they won't say that. They'll say borberigmy.
What kind of bowel elimination pattern would you have?
Diarrhea. So you get cramping, abdominal pain with diarrhea, borberigmy, guarding, bloating, distension, tenderness.
That all goes with dumping syndrome.
So if you get a dumping syndrome question and they ask you for signs and symptoms, how do you learn them?
Drunk, shock, acute abdominal distress.
So here's what I, hopefully you're, see, I want you guys to start violent things better, more efficiently.
They do test alcohol intoxication, which is drunk, right?
So drunk is drunk, right? You know that.
Okay, shock, they'll test that too.
Shock looks like shock. Do you understand this?
Now, if you take drunk and shock and you put them together, what do you have the signs and symptoms of?
Hypoglycemia, low blood sugar.
If you throw in some acute abdominal distress with that, what do you have?
Dumping syndrome. So I'm trying to link four of the major things they test.
Shock, low blood sugar, dumping syndrome, alcohol intoxication.
They all can be learned together.
So what's the protocol?
Drunk is drunk. Shock is shock.
Drunk plus shock is hypoglycemia.
That plus acute abdominal distress is dumping syndrome.
And you're just, see what I'm trying to do is get you keeping adding rather than memorizing four separately.
Okay, drunk is drunk, shock is shock, drunk plus shock is hypoglycemia, drunk plus shock plus acute abdominal distress is dumping syndrome.
Okay, number three, what's the treatment for a hiatal hernia and dumping syndrome?
They're going to be opposites.
Because think about this, with hiatal hernia, you want the stomach to empty faster.
Why do you want the stomach to empty faster with hiatal hernia?
Because if it's empty, it won't what? Reclux.
However, with dumping syndrome, we want the stomach to empty slower.
Do you see it's the opposite?
So you just remember one, remember the other's the opposite.
So what are you going to do to affect stomach emptying time?
Well, there are three things you can do to change the way the stomach empties.
You can play around with the head of the bed.
You can play around with the water content of the meal.
And you can play around with the carbohydrate content of the meal.
All right, so let's go through this.
In hiatal hernia, what do we want to do with the head of the bed during and after meals?
We want it in high position.
Why high?
That makes gravity empty and faster.
Okay, go down the column.
What do we want to do with the amount of fluids we give with the meal?
With a liquidy meal or a solid meal, which one will go through the stomach faster?
Liquid.
So we want the stomach to go through faster with this.
So we want the amount of fluids to be high or low.
So high fluid.
And carbs go through you really fast.
Carbs go through your stomach fast.
So if you have a high carb, will it empty faster or slower?
Fast.
So here again, you want the carbohydrate content to be high or low.
High.
Now, the dumping syndrome is opposite of that.
So how should a dumping syndrome eat their meals?
Low position.
Head flat.
In other words, how would they eat?
How should they eat?
Yes.
Head of the bed is what?
Flat.
They're turning to their side and they're eating on the side with the head down.
They don't eat on the back with the head down.
That would be stupid.
But on the side with the head down.
So low head of bed.
What about the fluids with the meals?
High or low?
Low.
So when would they get their fluids?
Not with the meals.
They'd get it what, an hour or two before meals or an hour or two after meals,
but they would never get it with the meals.
And what about carbohydrate content?
Low.
Because when the stomach is too empty, slow.
When everything is low, the stomach goes slow.
Slow.
Do you hear that?
When everything is low, the stomach empty slow.
In high atal hernia, you want everything to be what?
High.
In high atal hernia, everything needs to be high.
So when you see high atal hernia, you should say everything needs to be high.
What needs to be high?
Head, fluids, carbs.
And if you want the stomach to go slow, pick everything low.
Head low, fluids low, carbs low.
Now be careful.
What if they throw you a curve and they talk about protein in the diet?
For these two.
What do you think?
Low and high atal hernia.
Yeah.
Low protein in high atal hernia, high protein in dumping sugar.
Because if you're low carb, you're going to be high protein.
You understand that?
So whatever carbs is, protein is the opposite.
Any questions about dumping sugar in high atal hernia?
They're pretty clear.
This is a review.
So sometimes people say, Mark, I know most of what you're teaching me.
And I say, good, this is called a review.
So don't get upset when there's a lot of stuff you know.
Get upset when it's all a news flash.
Electrolytes.
How many of you in here can give me 15 signs and symptoms of hyperkalemia,
hypocalemia, hypercalcemia, hypocalcemia, hypermagnesemia,
hyponatremia, and hyponatremia with 80% accuracy?
How many can do that?
When you raised your hand, everybody in class went, oh, I'm not there.
Anyhow, how many can do it with 50% accuracy?
No.
You probably would have been able to get 50% with your book.
Okay, I went about 5% accuracy.
Yeah, somebody's, I got takers on that.
Okay, I'm going to ask you that same question in 15 minutes,
but I want to see what you say in 15 minutes, all right?
So let's talk about electrolytes.
To know your signs and symptoms of electrolyte disorders,
you need to memorize three sentences.
The first sentence you memorize is, kalimias, do you see where we're at?
Number one here, kalimias.
What are we talking about?
Kalimia.
Potassium, yeah.
Kalimias do the same as.
Same as goes in the blank.
Same as.
The prefix except for heart rate and urine output.
Potassium imbalances do the same as the prefix except for heart rate and urine output.
You memorize that.
Kalimias do the same as the prefix.
So what I'm telling you is, is when you get a kalimia,
just look at the prefix.
There are only two options, hyper and hypo.
Hyper means everything is what?
High.
High and hypo means it's low.
And your symptoms will go high with hyper and low with hypo.
They'll go high with hyper and low with hypo because it's doing the what?
Same as the prefix.
Except for the heart rate and the urine output which will go what?
Opposite of the prefix.
So with hyper, urine output and heart rate go down.
And with hypo, urine output and heart rate go yes.
So in your box there, give me some signs and symptoms of hyperkalimia.
Hyper.
Okay, start with the brain.
Give me some hyper signs in the brain.
Surely you can, you know what I'm talking about, right?
You're not that, I know it's the post-lunch flow.
Cerebrally, if it's hyperkalimia, kalimias do the what?
Same as the prefix.
The prefix is hyper, so everything in the brain is going to go up
and does the same in hyper.
So if you talk about the brain, what symptoms are hyper signs in the brain?
Give me some hyper signs in the brain.
Agitation, restlessness, irritability, aggression,
obnoxiousness, decreased inhibitions, loud, boisterous, right?
Those all go with hyperkalimia.
All right, well let's talk about the lungs.
What are you going to see there?
Taekyepnea.
What are you going to see in the heart?
Low heart rate.
Low heart rate, because there's an exception, but the T waves will be pink, tall.
The STs will be elevated.
See, the only thing that goes up is the heart rate.
Everything else about the heart goes with the prefix.
Okay, what will you see in the bowel?
Diarrhea, borberigme.
What will you see in the muscle?
Spasticity, increased tone.
What will you see in the reflexes?
Plus three, plus four.
And all those signs, what do they have in common?
They're all up.
Why are they all up?
Because you have hyperkalimia.
And in kalimias, they do the same as whatever the prefix says they are,
except for the heart rate near an apple, which goes opposite.
So what would you list for hypokalimia?
Lefergie, tachycardia, because you can go opposite there.
Tachycardia and polyurea.
What?
Bradypnea.
Bowels are going to be what?
Slow down.
Slow down. So what might you have?
Illus.
Illus, constipation, all of that.
What are you going to see in your muscles?
Flaccidity.
What are you going to see in reflexes?
Do I want you to memorize these lists that we're generating?
No.
Because you can get those lists from the saying that says what?
Kalimias do the same as the prefix except for heart rate and urine output.
Are you seeing where I'm going with this?
Your patient has hyperkalimia.
Collect all that applied.
Adynamic ilius.
Obtundid.
Plus one reflex.
Clonus, which is...
U-wave.
Depressed ST.
See what I want to do here.
Polyurea.
Bradycardia.
Okay, I want you to look at it and then talk to your buddy.
See if you can select.
Use the sentence.
Kalimias do the same as the prefix except for heart rate and urine output.
Draw your arrow.
You're going to have to draw an arrow.
And you're also going to have to draw the exceptions, which is the heart rate and urine output.
Oh, that should say hyper.
H-Y-P-E-R.
There's an R there. Sorry, guys.
Hyper.
What about the U-wave?
It says just U.
A U-wave. A U-wave is a wave that goes like this.
Fluffing down.
It goes what?
Down.
Focus, focus.
Okay, so everything's going to be okay.
Make sure you get all your arrows right.
You need to draw a general arrow, an arrow for the heart rate, and an arrow for the urine output.
Make sure you get them right.
The high person, everything's going to go up except for heart rate and urine output.
It would make them go up.
It wouldn't be there.
I don't want to.
It's going to go up.
I know it would be more important for this kind of the ops.
It wouldn't go high. It would go up.
It would go low.
Okay, how many did you select?
Hyper-E.
Okay, I selected two. Let me see if I'm wrong.
Okay, because I'm going to write my arrows out first.
I see hyper, and I know kalimis do the what?
Same. So it's going to make everything go up,
but heart rate's going to go down, and urine output's going to go down.
Okay, A, dynamic without movement.
Filiates, that's down.
That does not fit.
Obtunded, that is down. That does not fit.
Plus one reflex, that is down. That does not fit.
Clonus, that is irritability. There we go. That fits.
U-A that goes down, that doesn't fit.
Depressed ST, it's going down. That doesn't fit.
Polyurea, oh no, it should be oligurea. That doesn't fit.
Heart rate down, rate of cardiac, yeah, that fits.
Now, those of you that did three, which one did you add that you shouldn't have added?
You forgot to write the...
See, if you forget to write your arrows, you're dead in the water.
You've got to write your arrows. Then go looking.
Don't look first and then go back and write arrows. You know what I'm saying?
Know what you're looking for first.
Yeah, meaning of the words is helpful, yes.
The U-Wave, a U-Wave is something that starts on the baseline and goes down from the baseline.
So it's a sign of cardiac depression.
And the idea though, Leonid, is if you don't know what something is on a select all but applied, don't fit.
Because everybody tends to what? Overselect by one.
Isn't that what you guys did? You overselected by one. I mean, it's like predictable.
Yes.
What is octundid meaning?
Octundid is just a little more comatose than lethargy.
So you got lethargic and then as you go even more deep into a coma, you get octundid.
A lethargic person, ask me a question and I'll be lethargic.
Is it that same question?
Where do you live?
No, say that.
What's your name?
Mark.
Where do you live?
See, I was saying, or she's saying Mark Y.
I'm sorry.
Now that's lethargic. This is a pun.
What's your name?
What would you do? You're a nurse. Do what you would do.
You should have said, now what's comatose?
So, you can rouse them and then they go off to La Land and then you rouse them and they go...
Lethargics will respond but it's going to take a while to get it out.
Obtundids will never respond but they're rousable.
Stupor and obtundid are often considered to be the same idea.
Stupor is more a generic word.
Obtundid is more the medical term.
Usually, you know, I won't go there. It doesn't need to happen.
Calcium. Calcemias do the opposite.
Calcemias do the opposite of the prefix.
Which means if your calcium goes high, everything goes low.
And if your calcium goes low, everything goes high.
So hypercalcemia, what would you have?
Bradycardia, bradypnea, flaccid muscles, hypoactive reflexes, lethargy, constipation, right?
Everything goes down when calcium goes up.
However, when calcium goes down, hypocalcemia, everything goes up.
So what do you get with hypocalcemia?
Agitation, irritability, clonus, plus four reflexes, spasm, irritability, seizure, tachycardia, all that kind of stuff.
And you get two other things.
Shavas text sign and trussos sign, which Essie loves.
Trussos and Shavas text.
Shavas text starts with what? Two letters?
CH.
And what do you do to elicit it?
You tap the cheek.
So just think, Shavas text cheek, Sh, Sh, Sh, Sh, Shavas text cheek.
So when you rub their, when you touch their cheek with Shavas text, they go into a spasm in the face, their face spasms.
Which shouldn't happen?
You know, if I touch you on the cheek, you should go.
You know, and you shouldn't go.
That would be Shavas text.
What is it a sign of?
It's a sign of neuromuscular irritability associated with a low calcium.
It is a sign of neuromuscular irritability associated with a low calcium.
Why does that sentence make sense?
Irritability, low calcium.
Why does that make sense?
Because calcium is due to the opposite, so irritability would have to be low calcium.
The other sign is trussos.
Trussos is when you put a blood pressure cuff on their arm, you pump it up and they go into a spasm in the hand.
So it's a hand spasm when you put a blood pressure cuff on.
So Shavas text, you do what?
Cheek.
Trussos, you do blood pressure cuff and look for that.
Stupid way I remember this.
Really dumb, but it works for me.
Trussos sounds like a French name.
When I see Trussos on a test, I think of an effeminate Frenchman.
He says, I'm Trusses.
So that's Trusses.
I know it's weird, but it may stick.
I was thinking Jacques-Etienne.
Jacques-Etienne.
Okay.
So, Ford's test, those of you who are going to take Hesse, they will test Shavas text and trussos until the cast come home on that.
They love it.
Alright, hey, by the way, what if I change this to hypercalcemia?
Would it change the answer?
Yeah.
Because now you're looking for what?
The questions do the opposite.
This says hyper, so it's going to make everything go down.
So you're going to see this and this and this and not that and that and that and that and not this.
Oh, you will see that.
Yeah, you will see that.
You will see that, yes.
I'm sorry.
I got a little pen heavy.
You see, so it's really...
You want to call your colleague or your lawyer?
Yeah, you want to call your lawyer.
It's really good when you guys are better than me at this.
That's what we need to do because I'm not taking the test.
You are.
Okay.
But you see what I'm saying.
It really is more manageable.
Now, if they ask you which sets of these, like for the hypercalcemia, if they ask you which one of those was most likely,
you'd have narrowed it down to two.
Which two?
Clonus and bradycardia.
But because it was potassium, you give the edge to the heart.
If they're talking calcium, you'd have all these things, but you'd give the edge to the muscles and the nerves.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So there is that little...
But make sure it's the right thing first before you do it.
You know what I mean?
But if you're between a couple of signs for potassium that are correct
and they're asking you to pick between them, for potassium, pick the heart sign.
But make sure it's going the right way for the preface, correct?
And when you're talking about the calcium, pick the skeletal muscle and nerve,
but make sure it's going the correct way.
All right, let's talk about magnesium.
Number three, magnissimias do the opposite of the preface.
Now, some review books out there say that hypomagnesemia is not associated with hypertension.
Because it does the what?
Magnesium is due to the...
So a hypomag would result in high blood pressure.
Some books say, no, that's not true.
Check it out.
Go investigate and you'll find that low magnesium is associated with hypertension.
Okay, so some of these books get a little sloppy in their answers.
Who had that Zigzam cram book yesterday?
I was saying that magnesium is the opposite of high sodium magnesium.
But then that's what you're trying to say.
Yeah, a lot of times they'll say that when you retain sodium, magnesium sometimes gets retained.
So they say that high magnesium is associated with hypertension.
But no, it's really a function of the high sodium, not the magnesium.
If you're just talking about magnesium itself, the low magnesium has the high pressure.
But it is kind of related, but it is not a symptom of or sign up.
So what will Bortz do as far as blood pressure and magnesium go?
They won't even go there because that doesn't tell them anything significant about you.
It just tells you on what side of the debate are you on, that kind of thing.
Just a little thing about people have asked me about using multiple choice books to study for Bortz.
You know, those multiple choice books, what have I told you about them already?
One out of five answers is bogus in those books.
20% of the questions in those books are wrong.
They are wrong.
And when you do them, you think they are all what? 100% right.
And you start to doubt yourself when you're the one that knows what's right and the book is wrong.
So you have to be real careful.
When you do those books, do I want you to do them?
Yeah.
But how do I want you to do them?
If you answer and answer and you know it's right, you go to the rationale, they say you're wrong, what should you say?
What do I want you to say?
It's bogus.
I am not having my confidence destroyed.
I do know what I'm talking about.
The book is wrong.
I mean, there was a classic one on the exam the other day that you showed me.
It's asked which patient needs a private room.
And there was a patient with Cushing's syndrome in there.
Well, Cushing's people are immunosuppressed.
They should be in a private room.
The other patient was hyperthyroid.
And they said a hyperthyroid should be in the room because they don't sleep well because they're hyperthyroid.
And if they had a roommate, they wouldn't be able to sleep for a while.
Well, my opinion is between somebody that isn't sleeping and somebody that's immunosuppressed, there's no any nurse you ask would say, do you see what I'm saying?
So you've got to watch those books.
And then even in that book, which is the book I like the best, I think it is the best questions of any book.
I have real problems with it.
In one of the chapters, it said that hypokalemia is not seen with Cushing's.
Absolutely it is.
With Cushing's, you've got a lot of what?
Al dosterone, which makes you retain sodium and water.
Well, to retain sodium in the lupa henley, what do you have to kick out?
Potassium.
So you do get hypokalemia.
And then in chapter eight or nine, they ask about it again and they say that you do see hypokalemia with Cushing's.
So in chapter three, they say you don't.
And in chapter eight, they say you do.
And that's the state of the art of those books.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So when you go do these books and you know your stuff and you're ready to go, and it's telling you,
you know you're wrong, you're wrong, you're wrong, you're probably what?
You're right.
Well, they just, you know, I mean, they're not, they just, they're putting out a product to make money.
The faster they can get it done with the fewer people looking at it, the more money they make.
Okay.
We took three faculty at suitable took the Hesse test and we, there's 160 questions.
We disagreed with 30.
And your faculty would sit if they took the test.
They would disagree.
And with ATI, they would disagree with even more.
But they've never taken the test.
So they don't even know what's on it.
You see what I'm saying?
They don't even know what's on it and they're asking you to take it and they're making decisions based on something they've never seen.
And I'm telling you, they will.
You just, you tell them.
You said, you take that test, you take that test and you see if you disagree with it.
And they'll disagree with it.
I guarantee they'll disagree with at least 10 to 15%, if not 20 to 30%.
They really, really will.
But that's no excuse to get a 650 on the Hesse.
You understand what I'm saying?
If you disagreed, if you missed all the questions that were bogus on Hesse, you know what you'd end up with?
If you missed all the ones that were bogus and you got like 80% to 90% of the ones that really were valid,
do you know what score you'd end up with in Hesse?
An 1100 something.
You see, so that's not going to flunk you on.
You know what I'm saying?
I'm telling you two things.
I'm telling you, they have really a lot of bad questions on there, but those bad questions aren't going to be what?
Don't say, oh, they're going to get it.
No, you have to not know some things too.
All right?
Question?
Oh, I was just going to say, they wait so much on the ATI that if you get below a level, you get 15 points after the whole point.
I would just, you know, after you graduate, that's the best time to go back and just ask them and say, you know,
have you guys taken the ATI?
No, have you taken it?
No, honestly, have you taken it?
Do you know what's on it?
Have you seen those questions?
Do you know what the question, have you done a quality inspection of the product that you're putting,
do you know the product that you're putting so much weight on?
See, I wrote my test.
I wrote my final in my course.
So I know, so when I say you fail it, I say you fail it because I wrote that test and I know that test.
But a test I don't know, how do I know what it's like?
These products are not that fantastic.
The boards is fantastic.
These products are not.
So I'm saying, no, but then having said that, I'm saying that there's no reason not to get a reasonable score on these, even with those horrible questions.
Okay?
All right.
But I just want, what I don't want you to do is this.
I don't want you to learn a lot, know a lot.
Go take these questions and take a hundred of them and have your confidence totally destroyed because they don't agree with what you said.
Do you see what I'm saying?
And you tend to only focus on the ones that you didn't agree with, not the hundred you did get right.
You tend to focus on the four or five that you missed.
Isn't that the way we are?
So don't let those destroy.
How many find that doing those batteries of questions are the fastest and quickest way to destroy your confidence?
Yeah.
And that's not what they should, that you shouldn't even be doing them if that's what it's doing.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
All right.
So magnesiums do the what?
Obsidian.
Now, can you have a tie?
Could it be possible that a certain symptom could be caused by a magnesium imbalance or a calcium imbalance or a potassium imbalance?
Could that happen?
Sure.
So how do you break those ties?
Well, here's the tiebreaker.
In a tie, don't pick magnesium.
Why?
It's not a major player.
So it's probably not the magnesium that's causing the problem.
Number two, if it is skeletal muscle or nerve, blame it on calcium.
For everything else, blame it on potassium.
So let me show you what I'm talking about here.
I'm talking about this kind of question.
Your patient is diarrhea.
What caused it?
Hyperkalemia, hypokalemia, hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia.
All right.
Now, you know it's an electrolyte question, right?
So you know you're going to be playing games with arrows, correct?
So is this symptom up or down?
So you've got to find something that causes stuff to go up, the bowel to go up, right?
Okay.
Potassium's do the what?
Same.
So hyper makes everything go.
So could that cause that?
So that's a possibility, is it not?
Calemias do the same.
Hypo makes everything go.
Down.
Could that cause that?
No, that's out.
Calcium's do the opposite.
So hypo makes everything go up.
So could that cause that?
Yes.
Remember, they're in the same direction that could cause it.
Magnesium's do the opposite.
So hypo makes everything go up.
So could that cause that?
Yes.
So we have a what?
Tie.
So what don't we pick in a tie?
So we rule out D.
Is this skeletal muscle or nerve?
No.
So what do we rule out?
Calcium.
So we blame it on the high potassium.
Are you seeing how that works?
Let me show you another one.
What if it said tetany?
Is that up or down?
Up.
So let's do the same.
Calemias do the same.
So hyper makes everything go up.
So could that cause that?
Yes.
Same.
Down.
No, that would be out.
Calcium's do the opposite.
So low calcium makes everything go up.
So could that cause that?
Yes.
Magnesium does the opposite.
So low makes everything go high.
So could that cause that?
Yes.
So we have the same three-way tie we had with diarrhea, correct?
Now, what do we rule out first?
Magnesium.
The magnesium again.
Is this skeletal muscle?
Yes.
This is skeletal muscle and nerve, so now we blame it on the what?
The calcium and we don't go any further.
Now, let me show you what mistake people make with electrolytes.
Your patient has tetany.
What caused it?
A, a high potassium.
B, a high calcium.
C, a low magnesium.
Do you know what?
90% of students taking this question without understanding what I just taught you would pick for this one?
High calcium.
The high calcium.
Because they've got burned in their brain calcium muscles.
Calcium muscles.
If it's muscle, it's calcium, right?
So they're going to pick high calcium and they're going to be dead wrong.
Why?
It's going the wrong way.
You've got to use your sentences first.
Potassium's do the same.
So this could cause that.
Calcium's do the opposite.
So that's going to make everything go down.
That would be ruled out.
See how the answer that everybody would pick should be the first one ruled out because they're not using what?
Their sentences.
And they just think muscle, calcium, potassium, heart.
And they don't even look to see if it's going the correct direction.
How many think you might have done that?
Potassium is heart and calcium is muscle.
Now you don't even look at the prefix.
So look at the prefix first.
Then use potassium heart, calcium muscle for tie breaking.
Yes?
So with low calcium, or sorry, yeah low calcium, you pick that then.
This could cause that.
And this could cause that.
Okay now, our tie breaker is in a tie.
Don't pick magnesium.
If the symptom involves skeletal muscle, which it does, pick the calcium.
And you don't have to go any further.
But you've got to go through for the first time to make sure that your prefix agrees with the symptom.
You have to make sure that that imbalance would actually cause it.
Then you go break your tie.
And what most people do by mistake is they use the tie breaker first.
See what I'm saying?
They rule out magnesium for skeletal muscle.
They pick calciums and for everything else they pick potassium.
And they don't even look to see if it's even feasible.
That's the problem that people have.
Question?
All right, let's turn the page and talk about sodiums.
Do you see the one with the E?
I want you to write dehydration using it like an acrostic, like a crossword puzzle.
Put the D over top of the E and then write hydration down.
The one with the E, hypernatremia, is associated with dehydration.
See over in the other column, the one with the O, write the word overload down from that.
Overload.
Art, dehydration, and overload opposites.
So when you get a hypernatremia, what should you see?
The letter what?
E, which tells you it is the same as dehydration.
When you see hyponatremia, you should see the O and say that's the same as fluid overload.
So here's how you would use this.
The one with the E is dehydration.
The one with the O is overload.
And you're using sodium here.
So if they said this, a student nurse runs to you, the LPN, and says,
oh my goodness, I just ran an IV, a whole liter of IV fluid into the patient in 10 minutes.
I forgot to close the claim.
Okay?
I ran a whole liter in in 10 minutes.
I forgot to close the claim.
What electrolyte imbalance would you expect to see?
Why did you say hyponatremia?
Because they would have had fluid overload and you'd have been absolutely 100% correct.
Which patient is put on a fluid restriction and lase 6?
Hyponatremic.
Which one is given lots of fluids?
Hypernatremic because that's dehydration.
Who has hot, flushed, dry skin?
That describes what?
Hypernatremia, so that's the one with the E, so that's dehydration.
So here's my point.
If you had a 20-question test over dehydration and fluid overload,
versus a 20-question test on hyponatremia and hyponatremia, which one would you rather take?
The dehydration overload.
But what's the reality?
The exact same test.
Because any time you see dehydration, you say what?
Hypernatremia, whenever you see overload, you say hyponatremia and vice versa.
So in addition to a high potassium, what other electrolyte imbalance is possible in DKA?
In DKA, what other electrolyte imbalance is possible?
Hypernatremia.
Why?
Because wherever you see the word dehydration, you can throw in the word hypernatremia.
Anywhere you see hyponatremia, you throw in the word dehydration.
So what nursing diagnosis would be major for hyponatremia?
Hyponatremia, what major nursing diagnosis?
Fluid, volume, excess.
Exactly.
Or SIADH would have hyponatremia.
DI would have hypernatremia.
And HHNK would have hyper, because HHNK is the same as dehydration, which is the same as hypernatremia.
Is that sort of easier for you?
Okay.
So what do you have to know to know your electrolytes?
Here's what you have to know.
Calimias do the same as the prefix except for heart rate and urine output.
Calcium and magnesium do the opposite.
The one with the E is dehydration.
The one with the O is over.
That's it.
Now if you use those, calimias do the same as the prefix except for heart rate and urine output, calcium and magnesium do the opposite.
The one with the E is dehydration and one with the O is ozone.
Could you give me 15 signs and symptoms of hypercalemia, hypercalcemia, hypogosimia, hypermagnesemia, hyponatremia, and hyponatremia with 80% accuracy?
Who could do it?
And are you memorizing stuff?
No, because those lists won't stay.
Okay?
So, but you need to memorize what?
Calimias do the same as the except for calcium and magnesium do the opposite.
The one with the E is?
The one with the O is?
Okay.
So learn that.
Otherwise, learn your lists.
Have at it.
Be my guest.
Okay.
The earliest sign of any electrolyte disorder is numbness and tingling.
The earliest sign.
So if they said to you, what would be the first thing you would see?
What would you say?
Numbness and tingling.
Now, vocabulary, this word means numbness and tingling.
Parasthesia.
So forth we'll say parasthesia instead of numbness and tingling.
One thing they love to say is circumoral.
Circumoral parasthesia.
What's that mean?
Numb and tingling lips.
So that's a very, very early sign of these electrolyte disorders.
The universal sign of electrolyte imbalance is muscle weakness.
All electrolyte imbalances cause muscle weakness.
They all do.
Does anybody know the fancy word for muscle weakness?
Poresis.
You need to know those two words.
Parasthesia and poresis.
Parasthesia is numbness and tingling.
Poresis is muscle weakness.
All right, that's it on signs and symptoms.
Let's talk about treatment.
And the only treatment they're really going to test is potassium.
All righty?
First rule, never push potassium IV.
Everybody knows that?
Good.
Never push potassium IV.
Number two, not more than 40 of K per liter of IV fluid.
Now, LPNs, you probably don't have to worry about this, but RNs, on your test,
if the doctor writes an order for 60 of K in the liter, you're supposed to call and clarify.
40 of K, you don't call, you don't clarify, you just follow the order.
But if it's over 40, you question and clarify.
That's pretty standard.
Okay, three and four.
Numbers three and four.
These are ways to lower a potassium.
Why is the high potassium such a bad thing?
It stops your heart.
Cardiac arrest.
But what is the most dangerous electrolyte imbalance of a mole?
High potassium.
Of all the electrolyte disorders, the worst one is a high potassium.
It beats all of them because it can stop a heart.
So we need to know how to lower that potassium.
So number three is the fastest way to lower the potassium,
and that is give D5W with regular insulin.
What's that going to do?
It's going to drive the potassium into the cell out of the blood.
And it's the potassium in the blood that will kill you, not the potassium in the cells.
So does D5W and regular insulin get rid of the excess potassium?
Yes or no?
No.
What does it do with it?
It hides it.
It hides it where?
In the cell.
Does it really solve the problem?
No.
Then why do we do it?
To save their life.
Sometimes it's so high and that heart is being so negatively affected
that we got to get that potassium down fast.
We don't have time to get it down fast.
We don't have time to get the kidney kicking it out.
We just have to get it out of the blood as fast as we can do it.
It's sort of like your floor is dirty as all get out.
Company's coming in the driveway.
So what do you do to the dirt?
Sweep it under the rug.
And then you're going to get the blood.
What do you do to the dirt?
Sweep it under the rug and throw the rug back down.
Because you don't have time to really clean the floor.
That's the way this is.
With this we're just sort of sweeping the potassium under the rug.
Now what's going to happen over the next few hours after this works?
It lowers the K. Fantastic.
Now what's going to happen over the next eight hours?
The potassium is going to leak right back into where?
The blood where it could kill you again.
So what's the upside of this one?
Fast and quick.
What's the downside?
Temporary.
Which is why we use the other one, K-exolate.
Now K-exolate goes into your gut.
It either is put through your mouth or through your rectum.
An enema or ingestion.
And it's full of sodium.
It's chock full of sodium.
Now as it sits in your gut, what do you think it liberates into the blood?
Sodium.
But to maintain electronegative equilibrium,
what has to be kicked out of the blood into the gut?
Potassium.
And where does it get picked up by the K-exolate?
So the K-exolate goes in full of sodium,
but it trades sodium for potassium.
So when you depicate the K-exolate out, what's it full of?
Potassium.
Now how did your blood start out?
High in what?
Potassium.
It ends up high in sodium, so you have what imbalance?
Hypernatremia.
That's the one with the E.
So that is just simply dehydration.
Dehydration, so we give them fluids and we correct that problem.
So what we're doing is we're trading a non-life-threatening electrolyte imbalance
for a life-threatening imbalance.
We're getting rid of a life-threatening imbalance
and giving them a non-life-threatening imbalance.
But they still have an imbalance when we're done.
Now what's the good side about K-exolate?
What's the good side?
What's that?
It lasts longer?
It lasts longer, yes, but there's even, and there's a reason why.
It lasts longer, why?
It gets rid of the excess potassium out of your body, never to reoccur.
Okay, well what's the downside of K-exolate?
Well, yeah, you get hypernatremic, but that's not the worst downside.
It takes a long time.
It takes hours and you may not live that long.
So what's the advantage of D5W regular insulin?
What's the downside?
Temporary.
What's the upside for K-exolate?
Permanent.
What's the downside?
It takes a while.
So what do you think we do simultaneously?
We give them both.
What lowers the potassium right away?
D5 regular insulin.
As it starts to come back out of the cell, who picks it up?
K-exolate.
K-exolate and out it goes.
So, let me ask you this.
What electrolyte does K-exolate work with?
For calcium, magnesium, or potassium?
Potassium.
What's the symbol for potassium?
Now, does K-exolate make potassium enter the cell or exit the body?
Does it do it fast or slow?
Early or late?
Say that real fast.
So the minute you see K-exolate, what should you think?
K-exolate.
Potassium leaves the body, but it's going to take a while.
Well then, so if K-exolate in K-exolate, then what happens with D5W in regular insulin?
K-what?
Enters early.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So if you know that K-exolate in K-exolate, then you know what D5W in regular insulin does,
which is the opposite of that.
It doesn't exit, it enters, and it doesn't do it late, it does it earlier or fast.
Do the practice question at the bottom of the page using the rules that I taught you.
Do not use your normal thinking.
Use the rules that I taught you.
I want you to think through it.
Remember, if an answer is part wrong, it's all wrong.
And when you get an electrolyte question, what is it all about?
Drawing what?
Arrows.
Yeah.
Yeah, you can give it.
Yeah, cast your blue
They're going to ask about treatment that you're going to do on a unit in a non-covial emergency.
Okay, when answered did you guys come up with?
E.
How many said A? B, C, D.
Okay, how hard was this question?
Scale.
Scale was zero to ten.
Zero being easy, ten being unbelievably difficult.
What would you give it?
One.
One, two, three.
An hour ago, what would you have given it?
Air.
So what did you see?
What word did you notice?
Hypercalcemia.
Calcems do the?
So it's going to make everything go?
Negative ino, negative prono, negative dromotropic effect right on the heart and everything else?
Okay, so what's wrong with A?
Why did A not get your answer?
Tacky, killed it.
Why did B not get your answer?
Elevated.
Why did C not get your answer?
Tall.
So what was good about D?
Decreased.
Inverse, inverted.
Locked.
Right?
Okay, good job.
And you don't have to see, the nice thing about it is you don't have to, it's actually testing your knowledge of the principles of what it does.
But you don't have to memorize all fancy stuff, okay?
All right, take a break, come back, add.
Add half-past.